Inventory of the Papers of Park Elliott Dietz for the Attorney General's Commission on Pornography
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
Inventory of the Papers of Park Elliott Dietz for the Attorney General's Commission on Pornography
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
MSS 86-1a
16 boxes (6.7 linear feet)
Most of this collection relates to Park Dietz' tenure on the Attorney General's Commission on Pornography (AGCP), which conducted a year-long study of the effects of pornography in the United States. The collection includes commission memoranda, correspondence, transcripts of testimony, reports prepared for the commission, and various drafts of portions of the final report written by the commissioners themselves.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Park Elliott Dietz (A.B. Cornell; M.D., M.P.H., Ph.D. Johns Hopkins) joined the faculty of the University of Virginia School of Law in 1982, serving simultaneously as medical director of the University's Institute of Law, Psychiatry and Public Policy. In 1988 he moved to California to practice and teach psychiatry. In 1985, while at the University, he was appointed by then-Attorney General Edwin Meese to serve on the Attorney General's Commission on Pornography (AGCP). The commission conducted a year-long study of the effects of pornography in the United States, and made a number of recommendations in its report, published in July 1986. Most of this collection relates to Dietz' tenure on the commission. At the end of the commission's tenure, the Department of Justice gave Dietz a collection of pornographic literature which had been used in the commission's work. He deposited that collection with the Law Library in 1986, and, upon his 1988 departure from the University, donated it to the library, along with the materials comprising this particular collection. These research materials were removed from the collection in 1996.
Scope and Content
This collection of 16 boxes (6.7 linear feet), contains material dating as far back as 1973, and as recently as 1988, but most of it was produced during the AGCP's tenure in 1985-86, and includes commission memoranda, correspondence, transcripts of testimony, reports prepared for the commission, and various drafts of portions of the final report written by the commissioners themselves. Approximately three-quarters of these papers came to the library unfoldered.
In processing, a distinction has been made between official AGCP materials and Dietz' personal files, most of which related to the commission's work as well. This distinction was at times hard to maintain, but in general the papers in containers 1-10 are either material distributed to all commissioners as part of the AGCP's official business, or correspondence between the commissioners and with outsiders relating to the commission's work. The submissions and testimony from the various public hearings are particularly voluminous, as are the reports concerning the role played by organized crime in the distribution of pornography.
The first four folders in container 11 relate to the reaction generated by the report and the commission's deliberations, primarily from those opposed. The rest of container 11 and the remainder of the collection comprises material collected by Dietz but not necessarily sent to all commissioners or even related to the commission's work. These include correspondence of Dietz and his wife Laura, particularly after the AGCP report had been released, and materials relating to the ongoing campaign against pornography in which Laura Dietz appears to have taken a special interest. The last two folders in container 15 and all of container 16 hold clippings, some specifically relating to the commission or its report, and some more generally related to pornography.
Contents List
- Files of the Attorney General's Commission on Pornography (Box 1-11)
  - [Commission Memoranda], 1985-86 (Box 1)
  - [Correspondence to Commission], 1985-86 (Box 1)
  - [Correspondence within Commission], 1985-86 (Box 1)
  - [Correspondence: Miscellaneous], 1985-86 (Box 1)
  - [Correspondence from Citizens], 1985-86 (Box 1)
  - [Member Lists, Expenses], 1985-86 (Box 1)
  - Pre-Washington, D.C. [June 1985] Materials, 1985 (Box 1)
  - [Press Conferences], 1986 (Box 1)
  - Press Instructions, 1985 (Box 1)
  - [Work Session Agendae], 1986 (Box 1)
  - [Washington, D.C. Hearing], 1985, June (Box 2)
  - Washington, D.C., 1985, June (Box 2)
  - Washington, D.C., June 17-20, 1985, June (Box 2)
  - Chicago Meeting [Dietz absent], 1985, July (Box 2)
  - Houston Hearings, 1985, September, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Los Angeles Hearings, 1985, October, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Miami Hearings, 1985, November, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - New York City Hearings, 1986, January, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - [Ancillary Materials for NYC Meeting], 1986 (Box 5)
  - Scottsdale Hearings, 1986, February, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Child Pornography, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - [Court Decisions], 1985-86 (Box 5)
  - 1986 Data Collected by Police, 1986, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Dial-a-Porn, 1985 (Box 6)
  - [FBI Tape Transcript], 1979 (Box 6)
  - [Miscellaneous Reports, Testimony], 1985-87 (Box 6)
  - [Pornography Research Papers, Reports], 1980, 1984-86, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - [Organized Crime], 1977-81, 1984-85, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 7, 8)
  - [Prosecutions: Material from M. Cohen], 1984-86, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Social Science Findings [also includes correspondence, clippings], 1986, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - [Reuben Sturman: Investigative Report and Indictment], 1985 (Box 9)
  - Television/Radio, 1986 (Box 9)
  - ["Victim's" Testimonials], 1985-86 (Box 9)
  - Personal Statement for AGCP [Dietz], 1986 (Box 9)
  - Personal Statements [Other Commission members], 1986 (Box 9)
  - [Fred Schauer's Draft Report], 1986, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Schauer Draft [Annotated], 1986, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - [Various Drafts], 1986, (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - AGPC Distribution/Reaction, 1986 (Box 11)
  - Media Coalition [Critical of Report], 1986-88 (Box 11)
  - AGPC: Opposition Campaign, 1986 (Box 11)
  - Playboy, Penthouse Lawsuit], 1986-87 (Box 11)
- Dietz' Personal Files Relating Primarily to AGCP Work (Box 11-16)
  - American Sunbathing Association, 1985 (Box 11)
  - [Ancillary Materials: Miscellaneous], 1985 (Box 11)
  - [Anti-Pornography Groups], 1985-88 (Box 11)
  - [Article Manuscripts], 1986-87 (Box 11)
  - [Bible Advocate, 1985 (Box 11)
  - [Bradshaw to Dobson: Letters], 1985 (Box 11)
  - [Child Pornography], 1988 (Box 12)
  - Child Pornography: Case of Glen Foster, 1986 (Box 12)
  - Child Pornography and Pedophilia Report: U.S. Senate, 1986 (Box 12)
  - Citizens For Decency Through Law, 1986-88 (Box 12)
  - Clinical Psychology News Interview, 1986 (Box 12)
  - [Correspondence: Park Dietz to June 1986], 1985-86 (Box 12)
  - [Correspondence: Park Dietz after June 1986], 1986-87 (Box 12)
  - [Correspondence: Laura Dietz], 1986-87 (Box 12)
  - [Correspondence with Diana Russell], 1987 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence with Dr. L. Smith, 1987 (Box 12)
  - [Civil Rights Approach Against Pornography], 1983-85 (Box 12)
  - [Criminal Justice Information], 1985 (Box 13)
  - [Dietz: Non-Pornography Work], 1973, 1987-88 (Box 13)
  - Laura Dietz: Junior League of Richmond, 1986 (Box 13)
  - Feminists, 1985-86 (Box 13)
  - [Freedom of Expression Issues], 1982, 1985 (Box 13)
  - First Amendment, 1984 (Box 13)
  - [Justice Department on Missing Children], 1986 (Box 13)
  - Koskoff, H.: Film: "The Porning of America", 1985-86 (Box 13)
  - [Magazines: Assorted (3)], 1982, 1984 (Box 13)
  - [Magazines: Bondage], 1978, 1982, 1984, n.d. (Box 13)
  - [Magazines: Playboy], 1978, 1979, 1983, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - [Mail Solicitations], 1985-88 (Box 14)
  - [Michael McManus], 1985-87 (Box 14)
  - [Dottie Meyer in Penthouse], 1977-78 (Box 14)
  - [Miscellaneous Notes, etc], n.d. (Box 14)
  - National Christian Association, 1984-86 (Box 14)
  - [National Coalition Against Pornography, Inc.], 1986 (Box 14)
  - National Conference of State Legislators, New Orleans [May, 1986], 1986 (Box 14)
  - [Ongoing Campaign Against Pornography], n.d. (Box 15)
  - [Playboy Cartoon Studies], 1985 (Box 15)
  - Presentencing, Mann Act, 1985 (Box 15)
  - [Press Releases], 1985-86, 1988 (Box 15)
  - Religious Alliance Against Pornography, 1986 (Box 15)
  - Rutledge Hill Press, 1986 (Box 15)
  - [Schauer Articles], 1979 (Box 15)
  - [Sex Education], 1985 (Box 15)
  - Speech: Pornography and Health, 1986 (Box 15)
  - TV Media, 1986 (Box 15)
  - [Violence and Sex], 1986-88 (Box 15)
  - [Zewe Case: U.S. Brief], 1986-87 (Box 15)
  - [Assorted Clippings], 1978-(1986-87)-1988, (4 folders) (Box 15,16)
  - Newspaper Clippings/Popular Literature, 1977-85, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - [Media Reaction to Report], 1986, (2 folders) (Box 16)